[music]
>> Welcome to the 2026 release wave one
version of Business Central in launch
edition. This session is about enhanced
inventory analytics.
And inventory analytics is actually one
of the key investment areas in the
analytics analytics content for this
release wave.
We wanted to focus on supply chain risk
for the most sold items and also helping
you to get a lot easier building
reporting for your inventory.
So
just like we did for back in the days
like last semester for sales the year
semester before for manufacturing
we have completed the model what we call
the modernized modernization of
inventory analytics.
Everything you could do back 6 12 months
ago with legacy reports in IDE
you can now do either with Power BI with
Excel layouts or with Word layouts
or with data analysis. We are also
deprecating a few legacy reports and
moving the layouts from IDE into a a
more modern world of of new layout
types.
So highlights are new reports in Power
BI and Excel for ABC analysis then all
the way down to added analysis tabs in
the application for inventory. So let's
dive into it.
ABC analysis is a way to analyze your
inventory together with sales. So it is
a way to think about which items should
always be on stock and which items are
not selling
so much so so that you are categorizing
your inventory in three A B and C types.
You define what's the percentage of your
sales that should be class A B and C
they just need to sum to a 100 and then
based on that you can then do an an
analysis and see kind of for your class
A
items
they probably must always go on stock
because this is where you sell the most
whereas class C maybe you can live with
things are out of stock and and not
completely
always
in inventory. So you kind of divert your
resources for supply chain to the things
that matter the most.
The
analysis comes in two flavor flavors in
the Power BI app for inventory you now
have
an inventory also ABC analysis
where you see it that way you can slice
and dice based on your
ABC classes.
Um but we also discovered that during
this that in the German and Swiss
version of Business Central
it actually had ABC analysis already
whereas other localizations did not. So
we chose to delocalize that report move
it into the W1 and give it to everyone
and then
put an an Excel layout on it. So here is
the new ABC analysis Excel version of
of the report or the layout. It always
as we always do with Excel layout we add
a printable version of printable
worksheet and that's the one you see
here.
This report or layout comes with a
middle report that just a basic
structure of
cumulative values for for the different
classes and then and worksheet that is
designed for slice and dice with slices
on the type of the class of A B and C as
well as the inventory posting groups and
here you can then kind of dive further
into into your inventory based on
on the ABC class or revenue.
There's a new page in the application
ABC analysis setup. This is where you
define your thresholds they must match
to a 100. The same thresholds are used
both in Power BI and in the Excel
report.
All right. So that's
that's one thing but we also
looked at modernizing
the building reports for for inventory
and when we say modernize we mean that
we want to
put layouts
from legacy IDE into Excel so that users
can change the layout. We have also
improved the help in client and articles
in Microsoft Learn. So all of these
classic reports that have been in
Business Central for many years even
back to the days of NAV
they are now discoverable in all the
discoverability tools in client like
advanced tell me in in client in the
help pane in co-pilot chat
as well as in Microsoft Learn and
Microsoft Learn we know that all
co-pilots of the world also read all the
documentation.
Um
So for for this modernization we added
two new reports. You I showed you the
ABC analysis. There's also a new report
item age composition by quantity and
value instead of the old reports that
were either quantity or value.
So here you can see that um
new report and if we zoom in on the here
on the browser tabs sorry the the
worksheets
you can see that there's a printable
version both for the value and the
quantity and there's just one analysis
worksheet where both of these measures
are being shown. So here you can see
that analysis where you both have the
value and the quantity
for each of these buckets in the report.
Um
that's that and then for existing report
you can see I'll just show you a few
examples. Here's the inventory vendor
purchase report with the legacy layout
and here is the one that gets both a
Word layout so you can change that using
the Word add-in
but it also gets an Excel layout for
analysis.
So that's that's the what we mean by
modernizing a report.
So we updated these eight seven eight
reports you can see here to on the left
and then we are deprecating four the the
four reports will will be removed from
the product over the next three release
waves I believe it is. All of this is
available in 28.0.
Um
And then we got some feedback on this on
the inventory reports that actually this
is coming in 21 28.x. So in 28.0
versions
the inventory reports do not have
subsections or subtotals.
Um as you can see well we then
discovered after we
kind of uh
we put a line in the sand when when we
are not updating um the base app for
version 28.0. So for version 28
hopefully .1
we are adding subtotals to all the new
reports so that even so they they also
like are easier to to analyze in in the
analysis
worksheet.
Then in this release wave we are adding
the ability to supply analysis views
with an application in AL. So we're also
doing that for the base app and just for
item ledger entries in version 28.x we
will add these four new um
pre-built analysis views so that
when you open that in analysis analysis
mode you don't have to create them from
scratch they will just be there. If you
don't like them you can just use
personal customization to hide them.
If you want to learn more about
inventory analytics this is the link
aka.ms/bcinventoryanalytics
and it takes you to that landing page
within the inventory documentation where
you can learn much more about Power BI
um
out of the box inventory reports as well
as ad hoc analysis with analysis mode
and also these newly shipped analysis
tabs.
If you like this topic you might also
like other analytical topics such as
enhanced sales analytics all the way
down to enhanced analysis mode or demo
data for analytics.
All these related sessions you can find
links to back down here in the
description. Um so I hope that you watch
not only this one but also some of the
related sessions if not all.
If you already know the general Business
Central resources
if you don't then just stay on the video
and learn about it. If you already know
this topic
then this is the end of the video. Um
there's no more to say about inventory
analytics for now and I wish you a great
day and a great launch edition.
Bye.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners but also Business Central
customers. Most some of these are
partner some of them are also for
customers. So the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they are
called aka.ms and then for forward slash
something and with Business Central
links we all always prefix with BC and
then something.
The next one is our partner network
social media for for Business Central
partners Viva Viva Engage.
So aka.ms/BCVivaEngage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So this is where you can ask questions
interact with the product group interact
which is you with with each other
in a in a closed network.
Second link a third link is for both
partners and customers we are called
office hours. So office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/BCOfficeHours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events.
These are all recorded. I believe the
recordings are available only to
partners but the live events are
available to customers as well.
Fourth link is YouTube our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide
and then finally for for Microsoft
partners the BCs aka.ms/BCPartnerPortal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks
pitch decks and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn this is our product groups
LinkedIn profile. We have 30k or more
followers so both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
quote unquote official channel. So
follow us on LinkedIn to learn what's
happening right now
in in this in the around the product.
And then
also on our YouTube channel where this
is where you're probably watching this
aka.ms/BCYouTube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year but also
co-pilot and AI video shorts tips and
tricks technical deep dives under the
hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
on the YouTube channel before
they're coming in the release notes. So
watch
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube and
also notice all the playlists. So
the content is also organized in areas
not only all the videos. So if you have
an area that has special interest such
as analytics
you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
there would be no more. So thank you for
watching all the way to the end.
And again have a great day. Thank you.